I mean it's really an unsolved problem largely, you know.
Because a lot of times people have way too much
confidence in the agent and they get very lazy.
And that's
what concerns me the most, Imagine a skill or something that does an action,
but then to fetch more information to fulfill that, they get that from
like an authoritative source, which could have been prompt injected.
That is the invisible part where that's like not entirely obvious how that works.
At the end of the day, the agent is going to be able to negotiate the guardrail.
Eventually this access is going to get breached.
And that's the hard truth we have to accept.
The dependency on the GitHub workflow is going away
because your code is just not that precious.
Agents will actually find a way to, to to get into your website.
But if you want to make things easier,
cheaper and faster, well, WebMCP lets you do that.
We don't need to apply the last 25 years of software
engineering to the tools of the next 25 years.
You will be left out, you will be replaced.
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for developers and engineering
leads at the cutting edge of AI and agentic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple,
every week as we chat with the most exciting voices in
AI and tackle the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
Hey everyone!
Hope you're enjoying the episode so far.
Our team is working really hard behind the scenes to bring you the best guests,
so we can have the most informative conversations about agentic development,
whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or defining best practices.
But for whatever reason, many of you have yet to subscribe to the channel.
If you're enjoying the podcast and want us to continue to bring you
the very best content,
please do us a favor and hit that subscribe button.
It really does make a difference and lets us continue to improve
the quality of our guests and build an even better product for you.
All right, back to the episode.
Hi, Simon Maple here.
Welcome to another.
episode of the AI Native Dev.
We've just wrapped up another amazing AI Native DevCon in London.
And while we were there, we got some really smart people
together to talk about
some of the most interesting topics around agentic development today.
Coming up, we have my conversation with Netlify's
Dana Lawson, author and educator, Maximiliano Firtman, and Tessl's very own
James Moss, talking about the future of AI development for web applications.
But first the subject is security and I sat down with Snyk's Liran Tal,
Joseph Katsioloudes from GitHub and John Groetzinger from Cisco.
Enjoy.
So all of you welcome how you're doing.
Great. Thank you for having us.
Absolutely enjoying DevCon.
Of course. Fantastic energy here today.
Oh, it's good fun, isn't it?
So why don't we just do a very, very brief intro?
Tell us a little bit about yourself. Ten, 15 seconds.
Let's start. Left or right?
Sure. John Groetzinger, Cisco.
That's largely background in firewall, but recently, last couple of years,
more focused on agentic development and AI solutions.
All right.
Yeah, I've been doing dev turned into security
and devil thanks to Simon who has had that influence on my life.
Thank you.
I've been doing some AI security research recently, so that's been fun.
Similar background to around security turning more into
helping developers to ship secure code.
Let's see.
In the intro, you kind of mentioned a little bit around the kind of like,
you know, MCP security and vulnerabilities and things like that.
Why don't we kind of like start there and let's talk a little bit about,
I guess, vulnerabilities from a typical traditional software
space to what we're looking at now.
And I know, you know, you Snyk
and others are disclosing MCP CVEs as well.
Is MCP security and AI security generally now
where npm was like 15, 20 years ago, where
dependencies coming out and people just using them
because they feel like there's a massive performance increase,
but they're just lacking in security skills.
Yeah.
I think there's an aspect of that to an extent, somewhat.
It's the same issues and somewhat somewhere new.
So there is whether the MCP server, for example, that you're using is
actually like vulnerable or not, sort
of the aspect of the security of the MCP server itself.
And then there's like the consumer side of it.
So what are the MCP server you're using?
Are you like taking it from places and trusted?
When MCP came out, it was very hyped, like let's just use the latest.
So people would just like run it off as like command strings with like
you know, uvx or npx and then like the MCP server at latest.
So they'd get like the latest thing and you could like rug-pull them
and they would just get like new,
I don't know, dependencies or whatever would go in there.
So from that aspect, we kind of like haven't learned to like
instill the right practices when we're like consuming MCP is and it's
when we talk about maybe skills later, it's kind of like the same issue again
and again.
So there are some aspects of like AI supply chain and traditional
like npm package management supply chain that really, really affect
and and implement in the same way to MCP security.
And we've been through this route right before Joseph.
Like, do you feel like we have that muscle that has just been kind of like
it's already built there.
It's we know what we should be looking for, but we just need to apply
the same methodologies to, to other things like skills and MCP.
Yeah, I absolutely agree with that.
I think that the speed of development is so fast,
and we are all of us, trying to make the most out of it.
They are for security, keeps catching up behind these linearly.
Therefore we definitely learn learn from the past.
But awareness is not there yet, so that we are
starting deploying a new technology securely from the beginning.
That's why we have this gap every single time.
As mentioned.
And I guess, John, a large organization in Cisco,
like obviously, you know, we're aware of the threats.
What's the balance, do you think, between wanting developers
to to actually play with this technology so they get that advancement in
the agentic development, but also just being sure
it's done at a pace that kind of love for security
to best practices and things to to be put in place.
Yeah.
I mean, it's hard to speak for whole work, but we kind of go
team by team, win one team tries some pattern that works well.
You know, we kind of try to apply that broadly to other teams.
But I mean it's really an unsolved problem, largely.
And there's a new problem every week a different tool different thing.
But we do try to restrict access to things like OpenAI, for example.
Very few tools are banned at Cisco.
I was like, oh, can you get to this? Which is a good thing, right?
But our security and trust org is very intentional about what they allow.
And when it comes to coding tools,
it helps us get guidance from them.
Yeah. Yeah.
And do you feel is it very similar to kind of like,
you know, talking with security in the adoption of dev security?
Do you find it similar in the adoption of AI?
You'll have different groups of teams where some are absolutely
eager want to get started.
Others are complete. Skeptics don't want to even touch it.
And then probably the big bit
in the middle is willing to use it, but they want to see the value first.
Absolutely.
Yeah, I could see that so much.
I'd say it's way less on like the skeptics.
We don't really have many of those left
looks.
I haven't really found them. Yeah.
Top down is very supportive of AI and we know how productive
they can make us at the same time can be dangerous.
But again we have international security policies around around that.
So but yeah it's it's largely people that are kind of never really been coders.
But they want to try now because they can.
Those are really the ones that are kind of the most dangerous,
cause they put stuff out there
and understand the traditional developer security controls like don't
put public, you know, don't make your credit project public.
The basic things that agents will just do that they're not aware of.
There's actually a interesting data stat I'd love to kind of like share with you
both afterwards.
But you mentioned in a, in a, in a report, I think 83%
or this is maybe Cisco's data, 83% of enterprises planned to deploy a AI,
but only 29% feel ready to do so securely.
That's a start that you've seen or.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
What do you what do you think? I start with you, John.
But then we'll come across because this is a really interesting one.
What is not ready look like when we say when we say only 27.
Sorry 29% feel ready to do so securely.
What's a sign or a flag that says this is not ready?
I mean, sometimes don't even have
traditional security controls in like their pipeline.
So that's number one. If you don't have that,
it's it's a disaster waiting to happen as a first thing.
I mean that's just a key sign.
But I don't know that that's the basic one for me.
So yeah.
a good signal that things are very chaotic
at a company when they are adopting MCP is like basically
having lots of adoption, different MCP servers.
No one knows about them.
People just rediscover them using latest.
It's very fast to adopt as in like move fast, break things,
but at the same time it's it's early and not exactly
as like good confident security hygiene to basically adopt them.
So and what's the what's the fix.
Well I think at the very like we talk about like governance and policy.
What if the first thing you want to have like is like observability, right.
Like it's the thing that when we go back to talking about like
how does this correlate with like npm usage and like, you know,
traditional software development,
if you don't really know,
like all the packages, you're running, all the pipes and packages and stuff
across your team, you don't have that visibility.
If it's something that happens, like
malicious packages, vulnerable packages, you know, new react, zero day, whatever.
If you don't really know words that deploy, that's a problem to begin with.
And that's kind of like the same level with MCP is
and with skills later on and whatever.
basically you want to have a deployed visibility layer
for everything that Tim is running and your org is running.
So you could really have control over if there's like a new vulnerability
and you see a new malicious MCP server or whatever, you are able to actually like
find it to begin with.
And let's just like core beginning point.
You shouldn't try to have it. You should do or do not.
There is there is no try.
Yes, there is. No training
for those on audio only.
Liran is wearing a Yoda.
That doesn't sound a bit Joseph Heller.
You was not ready.
Look like for.
You, I feel what is
where are these stems from is from the fact that we are moving
in the execution layer and AI is taking actions,
can send emails and do all these things that people are getting nervous about.
So what is not is not ready feels is visibility, governance.
All these things
mentioned, I, I think it's totally normal for people to have a lower risk
appetite than accepting AI, taking care of the execution layer.
Therefore, if you see these
cases of executives in companies getting the emails being deleted,
maybe other executives are getting nervous and the top down
gets OpenAI being banned, which is the same as GitHub by the way.
We also don't have access to the website of OpenAI.
Therefore, I think not ready means that I don't feel empowered to leave
these agents to take care of the stuff
that we might lose clients for.
We might get hurt reputation wise and all these cases.
And interestingly, when we think about how we
how we actually become more ready, and actually a lot of it is education,
a lot of it is us making sure as the developers
on our team and on our organization know these types of attacks.
And in fact, Joseph, the session
that you literally just gave in the room, just behind that door, behind you there.
The it was a very much an attack and then defend.
So like let's try and work out how we can exploit.
Let's try and work out what the what the issues are.
And then how can we write better prompts and how can we set up our system
better to, to defend more against it.
In fact, it's very similar to the to the stranger
danger style sessions that you and I both gave many times at Snyk
and I think at at the the recent conference
Cisco Live in Amsterdam, I did a little bit of a session
there with the with one of your colleagues as well.
Do you find when
developers are more aware of the attacks, it actually helps them.
It changes their behavior.
Like when they understand the attacks, does it does it change the way they build?
Change the way they develop? Change the way they write?
Prompt? Definitely.
That's another workshop I gave in in Brooklyn
in the previous conference of Tessl there.
I think that when developers are aware of those they are
they are not going to trust AI to defend themselves.
They are going to build applications that have mitigated controls there,
such as, for example, output filtering or input filtering.
In general, they will not give access to anything sensitive to the AI agents,
because Eventually this access is going to get breached.
And by that, through sandboxes and all the zero trust measures out there.
So they are aware of those, I feel they are going to be able to do so.
Otherwise they are going to find out the hard way.
And that's the hard truth we have to accept.
And I would just add,
I think developers who are security minded are probably going to be
in that like box where they're always like aware of what could go wrong.
But even after many attacks and stuff, like,
I still feel like people do like npx usage latest,
just like watch the Claude Code usage stuff and like
I'm like completely scared to run that because I know the moment I do
npx — what could happen, like when I bring all of those dependencies
and maybe that was like a compromised package or something.
So I think it's it's going to be hard
to trust that devs and also beyond that, just like
developer citizens like now everyone's like empowered to be a developer, right?
So you have people who do not even understand that
and just build apps on top of Claude Code and whatever, and it's going to be hard
to expect them to follow security guidelines and practices.
So we should put all of that up.
And I think like, for example,
Joseph is saying like a really good job of like advocating all of those things,
which is great for the community, for the education.
At the same time, we had like built that into the workflow
itself, like have proper isolation and sandbox and how do we treat secrets
and how do we secure MCPs and skills from like a very
first principles kind of aspect so that that is already by itself
sort of like taken care of and like invisible to that,
because otherwise I'm not entirely sure that people are going to be stopping
to think about what could go wrong versus wanting to ship new features. So,
you know, hopefully the harness says do get better.
That's something I've said.
We'll talk about it in my talk later, but it's definitely
something we have to bake into agentic tooling.
Yeah, I agree, we talked a little bit about visibility and
I think it was like a key piece of, of of security generally.
John Cisco's AI defense tool
now includes an MCP gateway that actually allows you to to be able to track
and identify messages that are being sent from agent to MCP tool.
This is really, really important to actually identify.
Okay.
What's happening is is there
is there some badness happening from the MCP or something like that.
At what stage though, is this kind of like visibility versus security?
Like, is this is this going to stop issues or is this going to at least show us
something is happening and we need to stop using these types of things?
Yeah. I mean, it's hard.
I think if you can somehow observe intent, I think that's really, you know,
what was the intention going
in, what that agent was trying to do and what systems didn't reach out to
or talk to.
Was it really necessary to talk to the systems?
If you can focus
on observing those patterns, it's good, but it's really hard to kind.
Of setting the tone of what's normal.
But like, that's what I've been trying to focus, like, hey,
I need to add this rule to a firewall, I want the agent to do it for me or whatever,
and it has to do some Ldap lookup.
It's like,
I know what you're talking to Ldap for this, you should talk to his other system,
like instilling that in and observing the patterns.
Does it feel like still kind of like quite like
when you look at like a web firewall or something like that,
where you're constantly adding rules because things, you know,
everyone is constantly changing.
Is this something that is willing to just get comfortable with it
being kind of a little bit more reactive and identifying
these things are happening, we need to adjust.
Is that.
I mean, I wouldn't say in production reactive, but more, you know, maybe.
Developers using it.
Or deploy their test it out so you when it tries to do
before you put in production, observe that pattern.
I mean that's obviously what you should do first.
But unfortunately I think largely our learning to come from the reactive
happening and then we put a role in place that's just kind of how security is.
But you can try to be proactive. It's not
So I'm sure during the next couple of days
we're going to be talking about things like, oh, top tens.
And there's an agent as an applications top ten.
I think there's a new one coming out for skills as well,
skills development, which is super interesting things
coming out a few three key four time may be very, very interesting.
When we look
at some of the new styles of attacks that we need to be thinking about,
not just during development, but production as well.
What would you say?
Kind of when we go down the line against maybe Joseph, what would you say that of.
A of.
The most interesting attacks today, that we're not paying enough attention
to sort of things that exist that developers don't know about?
For me, this is probably injection by far.
I believe that it's a risk that we have to accept because if we
constrain too much the inputs they are, maybe we don't give the chance to.
People use
AI in the way that they want to use, which is used through natural language.
They are for.
I think we should be taking active steps towards the direction
of what happens from the moment that AI gets that information.
Therefore, assuming the worst, that
maybe sensitive data can be leaked, we can apply output filtering.
Before that, we can use the technique of a dual LLM jury.
Therefore, a second LLM with instructions to check the work
of the first LLM, which is something that Microsoft and GitHub do in production.
And by the way, when I mentioned
that it's a risk that you have to accept, that's something that we did as well.
We accepted that risk.
And for that we made sure that
since AI can be started in ways that we don't expect
through natural language and other approaches from attackers,
it's all about not giving access to data that it shouldn't have.
In the same way an employee shouldn't have root access or and apply
the least privilege principle in that case, and at the same time
making sure that these actions are sandboxed.
Because At the end of the day, the agent is going to be able to negotiate
the guardrail.
is going to be able to escape from stuff that you put around there
for prompt injection is a risk that can come from external,
but also from internal through the execution layer instructions
that we want to give internally in order to
do our work faster, maybe or become more productive,
achieve business outcomes in general and even from the inside.
We can prompting act in ways that we don't expect
or intentionally or unintentionally.
Therefore, for me, Simon, this is the most interesting risk that
AI brings by far, and people and ourselves.
We are getting slowly, slowly,
more exposed into it and more educated learning the hard way.
Sandboxing is like.
Something which just needs to become a default, and I probably tell
more people about it than I do it myself, which is maybe a confession.
I'm not happy to make it.
Yeah, it's something that we should just be natural.
Yeah, I bet you.
What's your what's your favorite. Are
you have to pick one.
What's yours?
Yeah.
I'm going to try and squeeze two of them in.
I'm going to build on Joseph's [prompt injection point].
I think indirect prompt injection is an interesting part of it.
So imagine a skill or something that does an action,
but then to fetch more information to fulfill that, they get that
from my source, which could have been prompt injected.
So I think that is like the invisible part where that's like not entirely obvious
to how that works.
And also the more you go into like complicated workflows
and how to like trust these like church party upstream, kind of like indirect
input and context into into the action
that becomes like a bit more messier to figure out how to clean that data.
Right. And how do you even defend that? Right.
Because let's say I'm reaching out to, let's say,
GitHub or something because, you know, I need some more data.
It's a perfectly reasonable place to go.
Correct. But it's how does you know?
Anyone can just like write some stuff
and a GitHub issue or a pull request or whatever.
And so long as it's right, so long as it exists,
you know, even with a trusted source,
you could get potentially malicious data that someone's injected.
So how do we even think about protecting?
It's a hard one.
I've seen a couple of examples of how to try and defend that.
One of them is just recently they're like, just like this research
that actually like run like actually like proxies,
the fetch of the data to like a dummy, like isolated proxy
and then watches the behavior of what happened.
So it's not the actual one.
It's like a proxy agent that you can't really protect against.
So you actually tell it to do it.
And then you watch what happens afterwards
in like an isolated environment and then judge that.
So it's kind of like a honeypot.
You have to follow it and then like judge it
because you don't really know in advance what would happen.
And also just because it runs well then doesn't
necessarily mean in a day it's going to cause data changes.
True.
And it's like so many exactly
like you could like fetch code and like what happens when you fetch code.
It's like, you know, like, understand the code.
Maybe that's like malicious, maybe not.
There are some signals, like when we did the toxic
skills research at Snyk, we saw like that.
Some like suspicious downloads would have like zip files
that are password protected.
So if you put something on GitHub that's password protected,
like why would you do it?
And the reason is like evade antivirus
and like malware protection that needs to like inspect what's inside.
So you password protected.
So there's like signals.
But again there's like signals. They're not entirely there.
And there's like like those there's like a bunch of like methods around yet.
But essentially it's like it's a hard problem to figure out.
So it's behavioral analysis plus whatever the agent is doing in its business logic.
Awesome.
So what do you think, John. What's your what's your favorite?
I mean, I think being.
Intentional about the questions that you ask is really
something I want my developers to learn because but that takes experience, right?
Many more questions to ask, because a lot of times
people have way too much confidence in the agent, and they get very lazy.
And that's what concerns me the most — just people letting it do it.
And then they just ask, is this secure?
And of course it'll say, 'I reviewed it, yes it is.'
And like what you should be able to ask, you should know what questions to ask it.
Like, what did you check for on this?
And then again
understanding the architecture how it fits into wants to play.
Right now I know it's sitting in front of some load balancer
which strips headers and you know, so it's like,
oh it's not it's secure here because this gets stripped. Yeah.
You know sometimes.
Yeah I think that's a over-agency in OWASP.
There is.
That one.
That's.
in a year from now.
We're going to be I know I know it's been on the week, but in a year from now,
organizations are going to be deploying AI agents into production.
Much, much more using it in development much, much more.
But do you think we're going to be more or less secure,
you know, usage in an hour, deployments of AI.
I think more especially in the enterprise setting,
maybe in the more smaller individual, probably less so, but in enterprise
it's it's getting locked down a lot more and there's more policies.
Compliance controls cost money, though.
So businesses, you know, don't always prioritize that.
But I have hope for enterprise.
But the individual is going to be tough.
To move from.
I would say more secure.
But at the same time we're going to watch some, I think, very chaotic
like incidents out there.
I agree, I agree with both.
I think we are in an interesting world.
Again, technology is growing
exponentially and we are trying our best to catch up linearly.
Therefore, I'm expecting some chaos out there,
but good chaos in the sense that it's going to be helpful.
I don't think mature enterprises are going to face major problems.
I think that small medium enterprises that maybe when I move faster,
they might be on the biggest risk because they are facing
the least amount of they have the least maturity.
And at the same time, vibe coders out there might be
exposing
themselves to a lot of security problems.
Let's see.
Joseph and John, it's been an absolute pleasure.
thank you very much for joining us.
Thanks for having us.
Really fascinating conversation there.
And from such smart people in our security industry today.
Let's change tack a little bit and talk about all things web AI.
Hi there, Simon Maple here hosting another episode at the AI Native DevCon.
And joining me here is another amazing panel.
We have Dana Lawson, the CTO at Netlify.
We have Maximiliano Firtman, the founder and director of codemia,
and we have James Moss, a member of technical staff at Tessl.
And we're going to be talking about AI on the web today.
So first of all, welcome to the episode. Thank you.
Thanks for having me.
I think everyone's first time on? No, no, sorry.
No, no. You did a session with Guy. Right. So
when I think
we had we had who did we have?
We had someone on the someone from Netlify on one of the earlier.
Sean Roberts.
No, I think it been.
Matt building.
Oh, it was magical.
Yeah. Better than him.
We're going to send this to him and and tell him all the ways that you're better.
Than you definitely do, because it's review cycle right now.
Oh, excellent.
Absolutely. Awesome.
Well, why don't we start off with kick off with a little bit of intros.
We go left to right here and tell us a little bit about yourself and your role.
Well, as you said, I'm Dana Lawson, CTO of Netlify.
I've been in tech for Wow.
I don't even want to say since the 90s,
I've been obsessed with developer tools and platforms for decades now.
I started my career as an individual contributor slinging code,
and have been working in this developing for developers systems
since New Relic, GitHub, have Teoh, envision, and now at Netlify.
So what a of what a set of companies to work for as.
Well, I know, right? Some good ones. Yeah.
And that's well before the AI era.
So I was a mobile and web developer.
I was doing apps.
I've been building websites for 30 years and mobile app since Nokia BlackBerry.
I'm not sure if you remember that Symbian and other stuff.
And so I've been a developer also a speaker at conferences in 75 countries.
Wow. Speaking and training, doing trainings and also a book author.
So trying to explain new stuff around.
And now it's a yeah everything.
And what's the country that you haven't been to that you really.
Want to.
Well there are a lot because there are 200. So yeah.
But the Europe most of I think we have all the European
all the South American countries.
And is there one that you haven't checked off yet that you really want to go to?
No, I mean, yeah, it can be tough.
Korea never been there.
Nice. Yeah. Vietnam maybe.
Yeah. It's nice. Nice.
James.
Hey, I have been building on the web since 1999.
So built my very first year of city
site back in, back in the day for my planetarium gang.
Anyone remember Planetarion?
No. Just me. Yeah.
And then for the past 20 years, kind of been building products,
mostly for startups. Right now, a member of technical staff at Tessl,
So I'm working on our registry product, amongst many other things, as you kind of
have to at a startup.
So yeah, love building on the web, love building products that customers love.
It sounds weird, but we've got over a century of development between.
The four of us.
I know I did a recent talk
and it was 150 years and it was just three of us,
and I was just like, oh my gosh, you guys are all
awesome.
So actually, Dana, why don't start with you, like you mentioned, GitHub, Netlify.
That's like two incredible like developer platform companies.
What would you say is different about building the web
platform versus a developer platform?
I think the difference is really the web is a lot simpler in a lot of ways.
There's not as many gotchas that you have to consider except caching.
And that's really freaking hard.
I think the big hard challenge with web is honestly just caching.
Trust me on this.
It's hard, but a development platform, it's a lot more open ended.
People can build anything they dream of, and it's usually something
very technical that's feeding one of these experiences.
And so the real shift is, is creating this office of stuff
that doesn't matter to a web developer and to how you power the web.
And so finding that line but very similar.
And with the rise of AI, the lines are definitely not.
They're blurry, you know, development platform, web platform.
It's an AI platform now.
It's just how how deep and what you're building.
Do you need to actually go.
And my hot take is you don't need a lot of the nonsense for building experiences.
If you're building a tech company.
Yes, maybe, but most most people are just building applications and websites.
Yeah.
So I think that users never cared to much about web or native
using the experience.
Yeah, right.
Sometimes they don't even know it's a QR code.
You think?
Yeah, it's kind of cure code and they use the app.
I don't know if it's web or native or what.
Any differences that you, you code to.
Yeah.
I guess when it comes to those, those kind of development tools,
you kind of
want to build a sandbox, right, where you want to build
all these tools, this environment that people can go and play.
You don't want to have those kind of guardrails in place.
You want to enable that sort of creativity.
And like Dana said, you kind of want to enable folks to to experiment
and get the tools out of the way, build something interesting, build something
fun, something that you kind of proud of and not not put those guardrails up.
Yeah. Cool.
You talked a little bit about kind of like
leaning into a little bit like agent experience there.
And this is something that I think Netlify coined. Right.
Agent experience. That's right. Yeah. Yeah.
So tell us a little bit about that concept.
What does it practically mean for when you're developing an app.
And you need to think about what the agent experience is like.
How does that differ.
From I mean, many of us don't have greenfield applications.
We're dealing with a lot of stuff that was written for humans,
and now with agents, it has to be at machine scale.
And so rethinking about how you approach that, you know, for instance, with CLI
is a lot of it's an interactive
and you can write scripts, bash scripts around to utilize the CLI.
But the way that it was codified was for human eyes
and for sequential movements of data and systems versus, you know, this,
this new world that we live in
where agents just work in parallel, they work in all directions.
And now you have different boundaries that you didn't have before.
Yeah.
We'll say like the funny when I play with Tessl
actually being here when I play with Tessl half the time I'm like,
oh yeah, I'm just using I'm going to use it through Claude.
And then I'm like, oh, is this using the CLI?
Is it using MCP?
And I just realized actually you don't know, I don't know and I.
Don't care and I don't yeah, I don't think it matters.
It doesn't matter.
And I think really agent experience is about thinking about how
those agents interact with each other and again, utilizing intent.
And so agent experience
is truly just going back and relooking at some of the systems that you built
or how you're going to build the new ones,
knowing that they're going to be used at machine speed.
And so thinking about that, and it's like you're trying to,
you know, run out all your threads, you're trying to kill the systems.
Well, you're not trying to.
So agent experience for me really comes down to two parts
is putting in guardrails, writing
intent with specs and making it human readable as well as machine readable.
And what does that mean when we talk about machine readability?
Because I think for us, you know, documentation, well documented
APIs and things like that, is it the same levels of documentation and agent
needs, or do agents need something else to turn how to address?
It's the way that it's actually written instead of doing gets and post.
Agents don't understand that when you want to understand
what's actually being pushed through its writing in, I go back to
some of the basics of Python.
When I first learned Python, I was like, oh my God, this is so easy.
And a lot of machine learning was based upon Python because it's understandable.
It's not anything that you have to go and compile.
You can just read it.
And I think a lot of when we talk about what agents needs,
they want that human view because humans are speaking to the agent.
So you have to speak in these parameters that aren't in machine speak.
It's now spoken in.
What's the intent in the experience that you're going to have?
Ultimately, that's really the shift. It's not magical.
It's just it's going to feel like dumbing it down.
Frankly, that's how I feel.
I'm like,
oh man, I've got to make this a lot more clear so that the agent
can take the correct action, because when it's not,
it's going to have to parse through so much
to figure out what those endpoints, what those services are trying to do.
Yeah, very much so.
I think coming back to kind of the key point
you were talking about there, about thinking about making those suitable
for agents, they are reading, like you say, they are reading
things like help documents in terms of how to use those clicks
passing in on the command line to read that.
But I think a lot right now,
a lot of people are still focused on human experience and then not thinking
about the agent experience and then not detecting that, hey,
the CLI is being run by an agent, not by a human.
And actually I need to tailor the experience for that agent and give it
perhaps more information, less information,
allow it to kind of navigate through the information
that you're getting out of that CLI as well.
It's like Max was saying like, does it matter anymore?
I mean, somebody was asking me, they're like,
well, what if you want to get in there and look under the hood
because you're a developer?
I would ask them, why are you wasting company money if nothing's broke?
Like, why are you spending your time?
Be curious.
Like, be curious.
But this, this version of like, spelunking for spelunking
sake is really just, I think, a personal fear of developers
losing their identity because now anybody can participate
because the agents are doing the heavy lifting.
So now when you go and you you look at what's happening,
humans are going, oh my gosh, where's where's where's my purpose now?
And let's take it one level deeper code.
Obviously I was chatting with Ryan on another episode actually,
and we were talking about code and human readability of code,
the importance of that person to agent readability and
the the parallel I drew was, you know, years and years ago
when we were writing an assembly language and binary.
This is machine readable, not human readable.
But now we've abstracted
into different languages where actually the maintainability was more important.
And so we made things intentionally more human readable than machine readable.
Now we're getting into the AI space.
We're actually going almost like the need is the other way around.
We're actually something that is more important for it
to be agent readable than human readable, although the human readability,
I guess it's more about levels of trust and level when we need to look at it.
Where would you say you are, I guess individually today in terms of needing
something to be code to be agent readable or human readable?
Well, let me give you an example.
On the web, let's say the web. So I'm writing a book.
The book is on Bonilla.
Well, I was always an album of using Molina Web, but
why are we using react these days with coding issues, for example?
So it's really needed at one point.
So because react was actually created for developer experience
for human development periods, it was actually needed.
But when you think about that.
Well, now we have other problems,
non-security issues with dependencies and all that stuff.
So maybe we are going to see coming back to some base,
of course we can get the extreme version and say, like Elon Musk said at some point
that code will disappear and agents will actually write binary code, right?
But despite that extreme,
maybe we are going to start
removing some of those layers at the top
that we had for human interaction.
Then maybe we can talk to the platform directly using just native APIs.
Yeah. James, can you sleep at night now?
I think we're in kind of a weird
sort of half state at the moment, which is really hard to reason about.
I often think about it in terms of self-driving cars,
those different kind of levels that you have.
I think it's at level four or level five is self-driving.
We're like full self-driving.
We're kind of at that level for right now.
You have to keep your hands near the steering wheel.
You're going to have to keep your eyes on the road.
And it feels like in a similar way, we're kind of there with code, right?
You're you're still slightly involved with that.
You're still kind of doing reviews,
and you still need to be able to read that code.
But ultimately you kind of do want the agents take more control
and for you to step back and not kind of care
about some of those details so much, but because we're not in
that kind of full state, you have to and I think we're definitely kind
of wasting time in some cases, thinking about
these kind of interactions between humans and agents,
especially when it comes to code
and how it's structured and kind of the quality of it.
Max, you've been teaching web
and mobile development for 20 plus years.
Five years.
25. Years in June, 25.
Year on that century.
Yeah.
What would you say is the kind of like the biggest mind shift
in recent times, now that you're, you're telling students
that they need to make to be truly not AI native.
But now AI agents have entered the picture.
What's the biggest shift that you've had to make in your.
I think that the biggest shift that I see right now
is that when you have new people coming to the web environment
that they ask you, but they need to learn something.
So why do I need to learn something?
So I my take on that is that we need to understand fundamentals,
how everything works. You need to have done HTTP requests.
So how effective been done that you have to get both
the image and the standard stuff, even if you're not going to write that,
but at least try to understand what's going on.
What are you asking if you're asking if possible or not?
Because if it's not possible, the Asian will try to figure that out with
maybe the solution is so complex that will not be performant
or will not be really the best possible solutions.
I think that we still need to keep for now that human criteria,
and for that you need to understand the basics at least.
Maybe you're not going to write code anymore from scratch.
You don't need to remember the API arguments
and how to add another controller or things like that.
But you need to understand the basics that when you're making an request
and you are going, you're pressing the back button.
Maybe you should abort that thing.
Things like that. So some basic ideas.
I think that they are still important about software development.
Unless until AGI appears, I don't know if that will happen,
not when if it happens, but at least so far, the differences
that that people actually starting from scratch right now,
they say, but do I want to learn that they need
to understand the difference between the and sections and things like that?
So and I say yes, because if you don't know
that there is a semantic and a non semantic
what's the difference in terms of accessibility maybe
is not going to do the right thing by default.
So we went very quickly from code not needing to be human readable
to now needing to understand the details of the div there though didn't we.
Yeah, but it's not that deep because of the deep.
It's because of the mechanics of it.
But things like that, even even when you are, you are making a semantic HMD.
It's going to be better for it.
It's reading the website, but it depends on the agent that you are using.
If you're not using the right skill or things like that, it's
just taking the average website out there.
So by default, when you ask when you are doing vibe coding
and you ask for an app, it's really it's going to make
an inaccessible application by default if you don't know what's going on.
So it's a little bit like actually Martin Thompson I think it was
you kind of like mentioned or maybe it's Martin Fowler, actually.
Mechanical sympathy, the idea you don't need to like
as a formula one race car driver, you don't need to know the inner workings
or the detail of how to rebuild a gears, a gearbox.
But you need to know
exactly how it works generally so that you can get the most out of it.
It's that kind of that kind of thing. An operator, I think.
I think you have to know enough to be an effective operator.
And I think that though, you know, there's not going to be as big of a need
to have experts as it gets better, and it's going to happen before AGI.
Yeah, we're going to see this before there's
generalized artificial intelligence.
And I think that the the bitter truth is adding in a bunch of glue agents
and a bunch of glue code, you're going to have to unwind,
because I do believe your point that it will get simpler.
We created a bunch of frameworks and harnesses and layers around code for
utilities for humans and human developers to go again, connect the workflows.
But now that the models are getting better
because we're doing great with skills and we keep feeding skills, the context
of the skills in in the intuitive nature of what you're saying is becoming learned.
And I think people
sometimes forget is it's large language model, but it's machine learning.
And every time we prompt, we are making the models better.
And as developers utilize the models better
and we create more abstractions that train the models.
The question is, is where do you spend your time, effort and energy
getting ready for this?
And I think we're a little ways away, maybe forever away.
I don't know.
I don't believe that.
I think we're we're going to get to the point where building web experiences
is as easy as sending a text message, and that's not too far from the future.
And so coming back to the laws of physics and science, understanding HTP
and the way that the internet works, I do believe are valuable, but
you're not probably ever going to touch that layer of the stack ever again.
Yeah. I shouldn't have to.
No, no, I kind of see it in the same way that things like the kernel, for example.
Right.
Like I've been mostly building on the web,
I've got some understanding of operating systems,
but I don't know how the Linux kernel works. Right.
And I don't need to, because it's so abstracted away from the layer
that I'm working at, that it would be a waste of time to think about that.
But I do need to know how HTTP requests work and how fetch works.
And that kind of one layer down is important.
And I kind of see it being a similar thing.
Right?
Like, you might want to know some of the the details of the mechanics of how
these apps fit together and, and how they're talking to each other.
But you don't need to know some of the lower level details,
and that will just get more and more abstracted as we're building
more and more layers on top.
And James, let's let's talk a little bit about what that means for when we talk
about agents being primary users of that,
when what is like the user testing.
What does user testing even. Look like?
Well, I mean, obviously the
big thing that everyone talks about right now is taste, right?
In terms, do you want the most generic app because you've got agents
to do all your user testing, and the feedback that you've got there
is just the average of the training data that they've been trained on.
Probably not.
I think that's where taste kind of comes in more than ever.
But your skill is that good tasting?
Okay, well it's solved.
Its own good.
Okay, I'll check that one out.
But yeah, it's it's one of those things where maybe again,
it comes down to abstraction, right?
Like a user testing works in a different way in terms of
you're utilizing agents to maybe user test things around like accessibility
or maybe some of the kind of large flows that you have within your app.
But for things like specific details around, you know,
look and feel, things like that,
maybe that's where you're getting a human in the loop to make those decisions,
and they're able to kind of sort of supplant
what the agent is doing to be able to enable you to do things like that
kind of a much larger scale.
I'd love to
talk about existing applications for, for,
I guess, a web developer who's maintaining that.
What's the what's the practical, first practical thing they need to do
to make that web agent ready.
For making agent ready?
So I think that the the first thing
if it's a legacy app, okay, it's it's different that.
I mean that means an app that I coded like two hours ago.
Exactly.
Yeah. Yeah.
But maybe it's a Java based or things like that.
So it can be really like there are a lot of websites out there.
So I think that, I mean, for the future when Phoebe is one of the solution.
I mean, what the future is, means
that different browsers and agents should implement that.
So right now you can start implementing web.
MCP lets the website expose tools to agents, tools
being just HTML forms or JavaScript functions.
But the first
thing.
So one of the so my, my my session at the conference was on.
One of the questions I got after the session is that.
But What about people that actually
don't want agents to access your website?
So the first question is that we will have that situation where
a lot of websites or worst of companies, they want want agents.
To have a web. No. Yeah.
Something like that.
So well, first if you actually want Agents to use.
I mean you are trying to try to turn off the sun.
It's not going to work.
Agents will actually find a way to get into your website.
But if you want to make things easier, cheaper and faster,
well, WebMCP lets you do that by exposing functions
that the agent can call directly on the the front end
on the browser session with the users context.
Local storage injected with accessing the camera, the user's camera.
Think about the.
I think that one example, one good example is the the meta display classes that.
Looking into the future, if we're going to use those AR glasses,
the meta display glasses, they have web app support.
So you can run a web app these days and they have an agent inside the glasses.
So then sometimes I mean, yeah, you can use your finger
to move around, but probably the Asian will do most of the stuff.
So then if you have a web app, an application that is running there,
you want to be more agent-ready.
And for that I think that will be the way to go.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's again it's it's you have to just accept that
it's going to be artificial users across the entire experience
from those that are accessing the site, pulling the information, utilizing WebMCP
to give the experience in another view or for the developer behind the keyboards.
And I don't think about this a lot.
And so at Netlify we started up an open source project called access,
which is just a scoring system that is completely open
to everybody to contribute, to get your systems agent ready.
It goes
through a series of checks and balances and some libraries that can come and see,
are our endpoints ready?
Have you made this change to your site?
And really, you know,
we're just trying to get the community because nobody has the answers right now.
I think the interesting part is like, how do you make a webs the web agent ready?
We're all doing that right now.
I mean, somebody upstairs is probably getting the web agent ready.
I guess the reality is there's not one technologist or company
to rule them all, that this is a time and space
where the development community globally are coming together
and defining these workflows, defining how to become agent ready.
And I think that's an actually really exciting part of our job
that didn't exist. I mean, I would write code forever.
Finally, we're going to do something new and fresh, even though I learned that,
you know, it's the birthday of AI and it's 70 years old, but it feels new and.
Fresh to me, I'll tell you.
Do you think there'll be a time when the browser will be legacy?
Oh, man, I don't know.
I love the browser internet, like my partners at Netscape.
You know, I work. At Microsoft.
Working at Microsoft was not great in Miami.
I was like, what?
I don't think it's going anywhere.
I think the browser will just be in a new form.
You know, you're going to have more heads up displays.
It's still going to be a browser behind the scenes.
It's still going to be the web.
But I do feel like HUD's going to come in and not dorky
Oculus VR, but but true heads up displays.
We're seeing that with meta as an example.
But again, that's just another it's another version of a browser.
It's just it's just http tcp ip man.
Well, the way down.
Yeah.
I think the thing for me right now is accessibility
actually feels like a really kind of like a powerful skill
that we should kind of lean into when it comes to agents accessing the web.
We spent years and years and years making the web semantic
like it's inherently semantic.
And and agents have allowed us to kind of like
make our sites more accessible, almost for free in some ways.
Right.
The, the, the, the training data covers a lot of kind of accessibility
techniques and best practices.
And so if you ask an agent, say make this website accessible,
it will do a pretty good job.
Right now would be amazing, but it do a pretty good job.
And to me, that kind of accessibility layer is something that works
great for agents, right?
Agents don't want to read the whole Dom like they don't care about the parts,
but what they do care about is the kind of accessibility tree.
And they can use that to look at elements on a page, interact with it,
and so they're able to use it as a human would do.
But I think, yeah, more and more of that will get abstracted away.
And again, just like code, some of these things just kind of won't exist.
Let's talk about the value of skills here, because I think
that's what sudden becomes very, very important with things
like accessibility and those types of things.
Given that skills are kind of quite language agnostic,
do we feel like there's going to be kind of like a front end specific skills
to help with things like that, like accessibility and things like that?
Yeah.
I mean.
What even is front end in a. World where.
Where a lot of this stuff disappears?
You know, as someone who is less technical,
do I need to know exactly what front end is?
You know, I just want to build a cool app that's going to help me to do specific
task or make my life easier.
And so maybe what we're calling front
end just becomes more of a kind of generic design element.
Whereas you don't need this kind of specialized skill of understanding HTML
and being able to take a design or a set of kind of requirements
and turn that into something that can be rendered in a browser.
So yeah.
So it's interesting to the front end and the front end
and back end is just completely there's no there's no we're all full stack.
We're all full stack.
There's no content management. There's no JIT.
There's just code. Yeah.
And to people that don't know, I mean it's again,
they do not understand that center of the hood.
And you have to start asking yourself, were these things that we built now needed
or can there
be simplification across the board to build and generate those experiences?
Because as agents become more prevalent, you're going to have
hyper personalized experiences that are just for you.
And those experiences
and those websites will be created on the fly, geared towards you.
And I think it's going to be really interesting on how we do approach that.
And I don't know if it's going to be front end
or back end, but regarding skills, I think for some stuff you don't need it,
but it's still very much needed for, for for governments outside of the web.
Like I would not I would not YOLO
without a skill for a database like trust me on this.
Like you would have somebody that doesn't know anybody.
Bork that database.
I've seen it happen because I was working on a skill for a.
Database and broke it.
I think that there's still a need and especially larger
environments where it really is a team sport.
On building to have a good skills library because if you want to make your company
participate and really think about the experiences that you are bringing,
I think skills are required because you're going to unleash them.
And so that's becoming more of the developer and the architects.
You know, Reign of Control is ensuring that those guardrails
are put in place so that people can safely do the things they need to do.
And and in fact, people already assume that there's trust by default
in these platforms.
And so, you know, do one wrong thing.
You're going to be in a newsreel.
So yeah, I mean, the lines are blurring of of what we say are front and back in
because now the experiences are ephemeral and they can just happen magically.
It feels magically.
But there's a lot of guardrails to make that magic happen in the background.
And that's where we come in and skills and stuff.
I think the content of the skill will evolve, right?
Right now it's very direct and it's like, you know, uses these HTML elements, use
this design language, this design library, these components, this front end stack.
I think what we'll see
as a move towards the skills being more about intent, right.
You know,
if you think about things
like the sole document for Claude, for example,
it doesn't have a lot of do this, don't do that.
It's more around what the intent is and kind of the kind of end goal
and what you care about.
And I think we'll start to see a translation of skills
into those kinds of documents, rather than just being a specific list of do's
and don'ts and a kind of checklist of how you. Want.
Things be really quickly, even the web and the premise that
right now we don't have models that are being trained every day.
So we are working with models that were trained a year ago or something
like that, which means they don't have the last year
of web evolution.
So that's when skills appear so they can teach the model, hey,
you have this API now and that API, so
you don't need to fall back to a library or things like that.
You should use that library, that based baseline library that we have right now.
Baseline is how compatibility works across different browsers this year.
So if skills are going to be useful
for for for web design and web development or, or JavaScript APIs
to modernize what the model already knows.
Yeah. I won't argue about that. Max.
Dana, I think it was about five minutes ago.
You said there is no GitHub only.
Only code.
There's only code. Yeah. I just want to just want to.
All I want to say is I think it was I think it was Dana from Ghostbusters.
Who there. I know.
There is no Dana.
There is only. Zul that it fits.
Well.
That. Is my GitHub handle.
DanaZul is amazing.
Sorry.
No, I mean.
I'm an ex-GitHubber and it pains me to say that, but
like the dependency on the GitHub workflow is going away
because your code is just not that precious.
It is and it isn't.
Because now with truly atomic rollbacks and the ability to fix fast
and create software factories underneath, there is still a need for revisioning.
Do not get me wrong, but the whole git workflow like that's for developers.
Yeah, that's.
What needs to change.
What's the key thing an agent requires in some kind of,
you know, whether it's consistency, whether it's persistence in something.
What is that?
First of all, what is that thing they want to persist? Is it like
the specs, skills, context, instructions?
What is the thing?
I still believe in source control.
I'm just saying, like I believe that source controls a company
won't need to be a thing.
It's going to be more localized
to the experience, or it's really more localized closer to the builder,
and it's going to be in the systems that they're utilizing to make the changes
versus calling back and creating developer workflows that are traditional.
Now, a lot of us have dependencies on GitHub, actions and all of the things
that we utilize for CI/CD platform or CI/CD pipelines to ship code.
But as CI/CD becomes easier and really, that's all that matters.
So what does an agent need to know how to roll back and how to push forward?
I don't care how it happens.
It just that's all it needs to know.
And you can use, you know, get as your version control or you can use
anything else because most users are most new builders are not going to know.
They just are going to say, oh, that change isn't look good.
Roll it back.
Going back to Steve.
Oh, we know what's new.
Again I'm here for it.
Directly to production. Like why not.
Why not.
Did you say you say this is what agents need to know.
Is this going to be completely abstracted from developers?
The developers even need to know about this now, all happening through the agent.
I think it's kind of a different set of requirements, right?
We keep talking about abstraction, and I think it is one of those things
I want it to be abstracted, frustrates me all. The time.
It's incredible piece of software, but it's also very, very annoying at times.
And when I'm teaching folks how to do engineering, it's often the thing
that is always tripping them up, right?
But it's great for agents, right?
And so I think building layers over the top of git that do that abstraction,
I also think we're kind of a point where we can start
rethinking how these tools work, right.
We don't need to apply the last 25 years of software
engineering to the tools of the next 25 years.
We should kind of use this as a bit of an opportunity
to rethink things completely and not follows those same patterns,
but kind of just tweak them a bit and get them to work for agents.
And are we going to rethink that?
Or the agent with the.
Oh, we get to that's the fun bit.
Yeah, yeah.
We put the humans back in because I know y'all have probably been there too.
You're sitting there by coding and you're up to like 500, 600 lines.
And you look and you're like, what is going on here?
Like 400 of this can be it's just garbage.
And you tell the agent, hey, 400, 400 lines of code, this is garbage.
You need to go in there and clean this up because I don't know what you're doing.
Start over. Guess what? It can do it.
But it also can do it.
Bad, bad, bad, and then good. And again.
We're not quite there, but we're going to get there.
Because every time me, you and others go through that workflow,
we're making it better.
We're training it, we're training it to be better.
And so where where is the line going to blur?
But again, we're pretty far off from there.
Yeah let's ask one quick fire question
where I'd love an answer and a brief why.
The question is, what would you say is the most important thing
that a web developer should either learn
or change over the next 12 months or so?
So why don't we start? With you, someone?
In the next 12 months, a web developer should embrace AI.
I see a lot of resistance,
a lot of people saying I can do better, a lot of fear,
and the best thing they can do is embrace it,
be curious, and start using it and becoming a force of nature
because you will be left out, you will be replaced.
The world is now AI native and our space is as well.
And so the best thing I can do is like, stop obsessing about your frameworks
and start obsessing about your workflows and start becoming AI native,
because the expectations for you to produce just got amplified.
Yeah,
I would say that maybe being a better AI user,
and that means, as a technical person, study a little bit about AI.
So: how the model works, what is the model — maybe try with a local model,
even if you're never going to use that one.
But understanding how it works, why context matters.
So understanding the context window,
all that stuff that maybe if you are a web developer, you have never done
machine learning or things like that you don't really know.
And if you if you're trying to use it
as a magic solution, you will probably get worse results.
So I think that learning a little bit about AI,
a little bit of prompting and why prompting is important,
the context, how the context is being organized and compacted
and all that stuff will make you a better developer.
Okay.
So I would say probably using AI to enhance your learning.
AI doesn't just have to be about generating code for you,
but what about using it
as a way to kind of interview about topics you might be interested in learning?
We've kind of talked about using fundamentals.
You still kind of need to know a little bit of those right now.
Thinking about using AI in that sense, I think is probably super, super powerful
and not be scared of it.
Really interesting actually, because actually,
one of the one of the folks on our team, Alan Pope, he's building out some of the
some of the Tessl learnings, and we're trying to build a learning platform,
kind of like one of the things I mentioned to him is we need to be skills first,
like create skills that are modular education modules that you can kind of
like plug into your agent and then do your learning
through the agent versus a traditional learning platform.
So super, super curious about that
donut.
Max James, thank you so, so much for not just presenting
amazing sessions and about to present amazing sessions, but
but also for joining me today and sharing all your wisdom and knowledge
on the on the podcast. I really appreciate it. Thanks. Pleasure.
Thanks for having me.
And and thanks for listening.
And tune in to the next session.
Bye for now.
Really fascinating conversations
throughout in both of the discussions here.
Hope you enjoyed the episode.
If you want to hear more from the guests featured in this episode,
their full DevCon talks have been linked in the description below.
So that's it for this episode. See you next time.
The AI Native Dev is brought to you by Tessl, the package manager for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI Native Dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit tessl.io/community to learn more and I hope to see you there.